<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The conduct of France since the peace at Nimeguen written in French by a person of quality ; made English.</title>
            <title>Conduite de la France depuis la Paix de Nimegue. English</title>
            <author>Courtilz de Sandras, Gatien, 1644-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20762</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18513997</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18513997</idno>
            <idno type="VID">205236</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20762)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205236)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1649:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The conduct of France since the peace at Nimeguen written in French by a person of quality ; made English.</title>
                  <title>Conduite de la France depuis la Paix de Nimegue. English</title>
                  <author>Courtilz de Sandras, Gatien, 1644-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hills jun. for William Cademan ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of Courtilz de Sandras' "La conduite de la France depuis la Paix de Nimegue."</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Courtilz de Sandras by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emanuel College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
               <term>France --  Politics and government --  1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205236:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205236:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205236:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CONDUCT OF FRANCE Since the PEACE AT NIMEGUEN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written lately in</hi> French <hi>by a Perſon of Quality, made</hi> Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Hills</hi> Jun. for <hi>William Cademan,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Popes-head,</hi> in the <hi>New-Exchange</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:205236:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205236:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Can't well tell of all Mankind, how I come to be giving to the Public what I now preſent them with; was neither by my Birth, nor Profeſſion, cut out for an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and without vanity
<pb facs="tcp:205236:4"/>could much better draw up a Regiment, than write a Book: Have made one however be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was aware, heard by ſome Friends of mine to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe pertinently enough, or as they thought I did, of the preſent conjuncture of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, engag'd me inſenſibly to couch it them in a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moire to the End, as I ſuppoſe, they not all ſpeaking ſo good <hi>French,</hi> as I perhaps might do, not having been the time I was in the Country, ſhould by the means be better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb facs="tcp:205236:4"/>by that Nation, as they happen'd to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe together. But as 'tis obſervable plurality of words ſteals from a Mans Mouth when Tongue is once upon the Wheel, fluency of Ink too is generally occaſion'd, when once People take their Pen in hand: The remembrance of one thing brings another into Mind, and when one thinks to be drawing to concluſion, wonders to ſee we again are to begin afreſh.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205236:5"/>
            <p>A Book then 'tis I have writ, as I told you, when I thought nothing leſs, and more, have let the Book ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Print; vaſt Field I had for ſubject, and could ſtill have had ſomething yet to ſay, would I ſay all I knew: But I conceiv'd this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently enough to let the deſigns of a Crown be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, whoſe Ambition reaches at more then it can graſp: Now as I make no manner of Queſtion, Ocean of Faults will be found in this ſmall
<pb facs="tcp:205236:5"/>Tract, I beg the Reader will forgive, conſidering as I have all my days profeſs't Arms, may be better at my Sword than Pen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:205236:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205236:6"/>
            <head>THE CONDUCT OF FRANCE Since the Peace of NIMEGUEN.</head>
            <p>THere is not any tho but little verſt in Publick affairs ignorant, what 'twas ſome years ſince induced <hi>France</hi> to make a Peace; She then ſaw the better Part of <hi>Germany</hi> United againſt Her, and <hi>Spain</hi> with <hi>Holland</hi> agreed to the ſame purpoſe, And though till then their Arms had all along met with favourable Succeſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205236:7"/>more then they could promiſe the continuance of, was glad to prevent with caution thoſe Poſſible misfortunes, which might have happened in caſe once their Good Fortune ſhould begin to leave them: But what moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obliged to the taking of thoſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, was, finding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſelf loudly threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne'd from <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Weighty Arms in Conjunction with ſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, were capable of Sinking Her to as low a Pitch, as She then ſeem'd Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in a topping Condition.</p>
            <p>It had been Remonſtrated by more then one hand to the Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that of all Things they ſhould lay hold of the Fair Occaſion to invade <hi>France,</hi> where they had formerly been the Maſters of many Fair and Rich Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, that whilſt <hi>France</hi> had her For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces imploy'd without, and her hands full abroad, thoſe of <hi>England</hi> would meet with no reſiſtance, means not only to an acceſſion of Dominion, but alſo of Glory.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:205236:7"/>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations, or the Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies rather that people had of the Grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Greatneſs of the <hi>French,</hi> ſway'd with them to reſolve to do ſomething more, then the bent of ſome Private In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts had a mind they ſhould: There being then a good underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and that of <hi>England,</hi> a Rupture of this Kind went much againſt the hair: The French no ſooner ſenſible how far thoſe reaſons I now touch't upon were prevailing, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſatisfied <hi>England</hi> they not only were ready to lay down their arms, but even to ſubmit to Terms. Store of good Guineys cleverly beſtowed in the right place, and amongſt thoſe moſt violent for a War with <hi>France,</hi> rebated imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately the paſſion, and rendred their propoſitions for a Peace the moſt reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable imaginable; upon the point of declaring, <hi>England</hi> was now become a Solicitous Mediator of an accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Propoſals were accordingly made on either ſide, and whilſt each inſiſted upon the matter of their right, which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205236:8"/>was long in debate without Redreſſing of the miſchief in matter of Fact, <hi>France,</hi> whoſe Aim it was to take <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> off from her other Allies, handſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the mean while inſinuated by her Agents thither expreſs ſent amongſt the Common Sort of People, How their State was not to be Retriev'd in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by the means of a Peace, that their only Shoulders had hitherto born the burthen of the War, and muſt expect to bear on ſo long as War con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued: That trade never flouriſht in a time of deſolation and miſery, and ſince in Trading their chiefeſt welfare, as that of their State it ſelf did abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſt in, the regaining of their Peace again, which had made that State once ſo flouriſhing, ought now to be the ſcope of their utmoſt endeavours.</p>
            <p>The ſtrength of theſe reaſons carry'd a poiſon not to every Eye perceivable, for though a truth it was the United Provinces did really ſtand in need of a Peace, they ſhould however have had regard to the proper Intereſt of their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205236:8"/>reſpective Allys, who for their only preſervation had engaged in the War. But as reflections of that kind went not with the Grain of the People, who long'd for nothing ſo much as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of their dear Trade, they made no impreſſion. They were beſides ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly harraſt now, and weary of War, for as the <hi>French</hi> had right enough obſerved to them, that State of theirs was forc'd to pay a good part of the Emperor's <hi>Brandenburg</hi>'s, and other of their Allys Forces, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned of neceſſity an Augmentation of Subſidies, &amp; Subſidies ſo extraordinary heavy that the whole thing it was rais'd out of, did not anſwer: And indeed a Man of Four hundred Pound a Year Rent was obliged to pay the <hi>State</hi> Five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and to ſee himſelf undone, and mouldred to nothing, without the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of a remedy: Every Body then ſenſible of their particular inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, thought of nothing but preſent redreſs, without the leaſt concerning for what might be hereafter: Of the whole
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205236:9"/>Body of that Common-wealth, none but his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> truly penetrated the conſequences of the Peace, which in that preſent face of things muſt of neceſſity to all the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lys in general prove very diſadvantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; ſince without lending hand to deceive our ſelves, we could not flatter with the hopes of Reſtitution from <hi>France,</hi> high, and haughty, in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of her Conqueſts; and common ſenſe might tell us, we firſt ought to have obliged it to one by force of Arms, before ſo much as the propoſal of any thing like it could be proper. Now to leave <hi>France</hi> in the actual poſſeſſion of ſo many important places, bordering upon <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> ſo cloſe, and ſo many Baits to its uſual Ambition, was properly by leaving him one foot in the Country, to give him the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of placing the other, as they ſaw occaſion; 'twas a thing not unnotic'd the great difficulty occurr'd in the uniting of the <hi>German</hi> Princes, which neither more nor leſs, but juſt like an Engin
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205236:9"/>of many Springs, was brought into motion, but with all the pains and trouble in the World: It was rational then Enough to fear, if once ſuffered to knock off, they were not when one would have them to be got together again; the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented all this at large in the Aſſembly of the <hi>States</hi> General, where ſome he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver miſt of, oppoſing his Opinion, 'twas flatly told him there, the Charge of the War was not a thing ſupportable, the exceſs of which had quite already drain'd their Bank, and reduced the People to the laſt degrees of Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; that a reſpite of neceſſity muſt be given, or reſolve in a very little to ſee the utter ruine of the Nation: That Prince would have reply'd the reſpite not at all like to laſt, and <hi>France</hi> ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but to ſever them from their Allys, having, once wrought their Ends, would again be playing over her Old Pranks within a Year or two: But Burgima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Ofteè,</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> ſtopt his Mouth, in telling the Provinces were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205236:10"/>indeed conſenting with all their Hearts to the carrying on the War, if his Highneſs could but hit the way of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it without<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mony, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Holland</hi> would give not a Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more towards it, or at leaſt the City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> would not, as whoſe Repreſentative he was commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd to ſpeak: Now you muſt know all the Subſidies whatever, rais'd upon the Seven Provinces, that of <hi>Holland</hi> furniſhes almoſt the half, and of that half more then the two Fifts are paid by the City of <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> That in the <hi>Quota</hi> of Subſidies if the Province of <hi>Holland</hi> be reckon'd to pay Fifteen Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, of that Fifteen, Seven is near pay'd by that City.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Ofteè</hi>'s having thus declar'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf there was no likelihood of thinking to continue the War any longer, chiefly for that the reſt of the Provinces confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for the moſt part in Opinion much with that of <hi>Holland,</hi> was eaſily obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, and that though they yet had not explain'd themſelves ſo fully upon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205236:10"/>the point as <hi>Holland</hi> had, their great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to Peace was like their's appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently obvious. As the Emperor tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly underſtood at bottom, the <hi>French</hi> intentions drove of a long time at Univerſal Monarchy, at hearing what had paſt in <hi>Holland</hi> was much concern'd at the News: Yet to divert if poſſible thoſe Provinces from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions they had taken, had it told them, he required no more of them the Subſidies they us'd to pay him, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to return them again upon the like occaſion the ſame aſſiſtance: The <hi>Hollanders</hi> thank't the Emperor for his good will, but could not be induced for that to continue the War, adding that ſeeing his Imperial Majeſty as well as the reſt of the Allys produced every day ſome freſh Obſtacles or other to the Peace then in Treaty at <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> warn'd him, that if he did not think good to conclude the Peace, and that very ſuddenly, they ſhould be oblig'd to do it without him; what made the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſo preſſing was, that as <hi>France</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:205236:11"/>laid the conditions of the Treaty very diſadvantageous to the reſt of the Allys, as advantageous and beneficial were the Terms ſhe made for <hi>Holland,</hi> for <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrícht</hi> they offer'd to reſtore, the only remaining place of all their Conqueſts, upon that State ſince the firſt of the War, ſo that though once reduced within an Inch of their Deſtruction entire, they were now in proſpect of a re-eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Vertue of the Peace to the ſame it ever had in times of its great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Proſperity: Something too there was over and above that careſs't their Courage in the propoſed Treaty, as they ſaw the King of <hi>France</hi> made it his buſineſs to diſtinguiſh them from the other Allys, they thence imagin'd they ſhould retrieve their loſt reputation amongſt other Nations, who formerly held their Forces in ſuch good Opinion, and ſhould yet think very well of them, ſeeing they were able to make their party good, and to defend themſelves againſt a prevailing Power ſo very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable: To ſay the Truth 'tis won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205236:11"/>ſtrange, and worthy without doubt of the admiration of Poſterity for ever, that a little Nook of Land, as one may ſay, and Handful of People, has not been only able to withſtand ſuch mighty Armies, but likewiſe in condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to afford ſuccour to her Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. 'Twill be ſubject of ſurprize enough to them who ſhall ſucceed us, to read in Hiſtory, that <hi>Hollanders, Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rreconcilable Enemies, ſhould be the People who have ſav'd the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> nor the <hi>Spaniards</hi> heretofore ſo inveterate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Hollanders,</hi> to find no where a more firm ſupport, nor a more ready aſſiſtance, then that they receiv'd at hands of their moſt Ancient Enemies: That by a fetch of Fortune ſo very ſtrange, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> muſt have been ruin'd had thoſe of <hi>Holland</hi> never revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſubjection, &amp; ſhould there come to find their ſafety, where they ever reckon'd on as their certain Deſtruction: One may well enough ſay the <hi>Hollanders</hi> have twice ſcap't
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205236:12"/>a ſcowring, by their freeing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Tyranny of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> for had they ſtill continued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Dominion, the whole Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Provinces had equally been loſt. And indeed there needs no ſtreſs of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks to diſcover the ſafety, and well being, of the United Provinces, is meerly to be own'd to the prudent conduct of thoſe who were at Helm, as a peculiar reward in ſtore from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for what their Fore-Fathers had endured for their Religion's ſake:</p>
            <p>But to reſume my Diſcourſe, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ſuffering themſelves to be thus over-reach't by all thoſe gloſſy appearances, ſigned cheerfully to the Peace apart, ſeeing their Allys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd obſtinate in purſuing of the War, contrary to their Opinion; I ſhall neither ſay in doing ſo they did well or ill, one may judge enough of it by what ſince has happen'd: The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, however and <hi>Spaniard,</hi> finding their ſtrongeſt recourſe had thus aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd them, accepted of the Peace on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:205236:12"/>their ſide too, and in like manner aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd the Duke of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> who could not be brought to admit of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions offer'd him ſo very prejudicial. <hi>France</hi> then direct'd her Arms that way, and as that Elector was not of himſelf to reſiſt alone, did what ſeem'd good in her Eyes in Treaty with that Prince, with this comfort at the leaſt, what he was forc't to by <hi>France,</hi> was with his Sword in his Hand, and that his laſt action did not derogate from a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand others, wherein he had during the War ſo worthily behav'd himſelf: The Peace being then ſo happily finiſht to the content of <hi>France,</hi> as it rather had ſuſpended then relinquiſht its deſign of Univerſal Monarchy, began now to manage thoſe Princes ſhe ſaw divided, where there was ground to hope ſhe might do it to effect, The Duke of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> could not be well more diſcontented with the Emperor, then he then was, obliged to reſtore back all he had made Conqueſt of, without the leaſt ſhew of the Imperial aſſiſtance,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205236:13"/>
               <hi>France</hi> therefore propoſes an Alliance with him, with high Promiſes of a more Honorable Faith then he had yet found with any of the other; at the ſame time the <hi>French</hi> Money was not wanting in its Benevolencies to that Court for the acquiring of ſome confiding Perſon proper for the backing their deſign, and ſoothed was that Elector with the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a prop from ſuch a Crown as ſhak't beſides thoſe of all its Neighbours, great things were offer'd him and to ſay in a word his reſolutions in the Matter ſtagger'd by Thouſand of advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tempting proffers. He did ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ject though againſt the project of that Alliance his Diſputes with <hi>Swede</hi> at that time ſiding with the Intereſt of <hi>France,</hi> &amp; as thoſe Diſputes have often produc't but ill effects, 'tis not forreign to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for the Readers better inſtruction, to diſcourſe it in a word or two.</p>
            <p>A certain Marquis of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> made in former time ſome agreement with the Duke of <hi>Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rania</hi> by which they ſettled their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205236:13"/>Dominions reſpectively upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to their Children after them of both Parties in caſe any who ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of either ſhould happen to deceaſe without Iſſue of his Body: The Entail taking place, and the Duke of <hi>Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rania</hi> dying without Iſſue ſome Two hundred years ago, or thereabouts, the Marquis of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> by Virtue of the ſaid Settlement ſucceeded to the Dutchy of <hi>Pomerania</hi> remaining the peaceable Poſſeſſor thereof till the Great <hi>Guſtavus</hi> took it from him by force of Arms: <hi>Guſtavus</hi> or his Succeſſors were confirmed in their poſſeſſion of that Country by the Treaty of <hi>Munſter,</hi> but as the Marquis thereunto conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but with regret and <hi>per</hi> force, a ſecret certain inckling of having it again has remain'd, which ſo often as the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on preſents him 'tis not to be doubted but he makes it his endeavor. When <hi>France</hi> then underſtood what 'twas ſtuck with the Duke of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and hinder'd his engaging in her Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts in favour of him ſhe reſolv'd to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:205236:14"/>make a Sacrifice of <hi>Swede,</hi> but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to it, made firſt ſure of the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> for that Crown, then in conjunction with <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> found her ſelf by the projection of that Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy of Strength enough in the North, not to fear what the reſt of its Princes might be undertaking in oppoſition to the <hi>French</hi> deſigns: The King of <hi>Denmark</hi> who had a ſample himſelf like others of the Puiſſant force of <hi>France</hi> in the laſt War, rejected not the Alliance; but as <hi>Brandenburg</hi> had before oppoſed the interferings too of his Intereſt with that of <hi>Swede,</hi> let <hi>France</hi> underſtand it only declin'd Propoſals upon that account: <hi>France</hi> was otherwiſe not over ſatisfied with <hi>Swede,</hi> for its hove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as one may call it ſo long about the Matter before it could finally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it ſelf in the late War, that after its declaring, had acted nothing an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to that high Reputation the great <hi>Guſtavus</hi> had gain'd his Nation by the great things he had done, that far from managing as formerly that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:205236:14"/>People ſeem'd to have no great regard of upon ſeveral occaſions.</p>
            <p>The firſt token ſhe gave of this was in the pretentions ſhe made appear relating to Homage claim'd for the Dutchy of <hi>Deux-ponts</hi> of which ſhe was got ſeized in the War time, even in the life of its late Duke, upon pretext of keeping it for the King of <hi>Swedes</hi> Uſe, who was then the preſumptive Heir, but in effect to keep it for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to make their own uſes of it, for the Promotion of their Deſigns: And ſince it here falls out to treat of the Fealty and Homage that Crown lays claim to from ſo many Sovereign Heads, 'twill not be improper to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late upon what bottom that <hi>Chimera</hi> is grounded, &amp; which at this very time is the coercive cauſe why the quiet of all <hi>Europe</hi> is ſo unhappily diſturbed.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Metz</hi> there is a Sovereign ſort of Court of Judicature, and a Solicitor Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral belonging to it, who having had commands from the King of <hi>France</hi> to give in an exact Memoir of all that ever
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205236:15"/>was within the juriſdiction, limits, and precinct of that Parliament, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit up the ſame to Court, he preſently fills his Paper with ſeveral Villages which never had been belonging, but withal with their remarks upon them, how they had been formerly ſeparatd, &amp; how they had acknowledged the juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of other Neighbouring Princes who had been very well ſatisfied to U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp that Power. The Inſtrument was drawn with Argument enough, and though it might want a foundation, did not want for colour and pretext; the State Miniſters reliſhing the Draft, Mr. Solicitor General is forthwith ſent for to Court, to help clear ſome few Scruples, which yet remain'd upon their Mind, the Solicitor come not only maintain'd what he had before ſent up, but pleaſing of himſelf with the offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous part of uſeful Man depoſes he had found ſome old Records by which it was to be made out that the Dutchy of <hi>Deux-ponts</hi> had ever held of the Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick, and that many more conſiderable
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:205236:15"/>Lands by the connivance, and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the ſeveral Biſhops with their own private Relations had been alienated and diſmember'd, for that thoſe Biſhops being but Tenants for life, were well enough content in Eſtates of eaſie acquiſition to accommodate their reſpective Families with the convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Church-Lands. The <hi>French</hi> Miniſters ſavour'd well the Opinion of Mr. Solicitor, and order'd him dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to inſpect all publick Regiſters, for what might there be found of New, and thereof to forthwith make an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract with Care, to be afterwards made uſe of in time &amp; place. But to avoid a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality which all ſhould do, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take a publick Information; ſomething there was of what Mr. Solicitor did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for many of the Good Biſhops to oblige their Kindred, had truly let them have ſome Lands within their particular Donation, but in exchange had received other Lands back again in lieu; ſo that thoſe Lands in Juſtice ought to be reſtored again which had
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205236:16"/>been given to the Biſhops, or to what had been alienated and granted by the Biſhops to make no pretence. But to the thred of my Diſcourſe, the Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor General was no ſooner return'd home again to <hi>Metz,</hi> but fell a ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching not only all the public Regiſters, but too of all the old Archives of Churches and Abbeys he could lay his Hand on, and as he was provided with Commiſſion from above Expreſs, ſwept them all away without the act of any Witneſs or making of the leaſt Invento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the point, which he ought not to have done, that every Body that way might have the better underſtood what properly pertain'd to them, and that the Jealouſie ſince conceived of the great Antiquity of thoſe Parchments, (not ſo very Old as made believe) might ſo have been remov'd; ſo be it Mr. <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor</hi> was obſerv'd long cloſeted cloſe up about fixing his <hi>Memoirs,</hi> which having fram'd as he pleas'd himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns again to Court ſwell'd with the preſumption of an Eminent Service, not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205236:16"/>doubting what he brought could be ill received: Now the Contents of thoſe <hi>Memoirs</hi> are the pretenſions which we have ſince ſeen break out, and at this day make ſuch a rattle all <hi>Europe</hi> over.</p>
            <p>The Marquis of <hi>Louvois</hi> State-Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary at Wars, who has a very great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in that Kingdom, whom Mr. Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor preſented his Memoirs to, could not at ſight of them forbear laughing, for tho 'twas his Buſineſs more then any Bodies to diſturb the Peace which turned not to that account time of War might do, perceiving little in them that would hold Water, was not ſo willing to expoſe his Maſter upon a light occaſion, who when he had mind to be making of a War, wanted not variety of ſpecious pretexts: He would needs know tho of the Solicitor whence he had fiſht all thoſe Diſcoveries; Mr. Solicitor Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſeeing him ſo hard of belief draws out of his Pocket another Schedule which contain'd the Dates of all the true and falſe deeds from out of which he had collected the Inſtrument he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:205236:17"/>had given in; as Mr. Solicitor propoſed to himſelf the making of a great fortune from the ſucceſs of that Affair he ſo cloſely ply'd Mr. <hi>De Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vois</hi> with the Scheme of ſo many uſeful things that at laſt prevail'd with that Miniſter to promiſe, when at better lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the full peruſal of his Memoir, and thereon to return his Anſwer.</p>
            <p>The Anſwer to Mr. Solicitor prov'd more in his Favour then off hand the firſt Reception had given him reaſon to expect: Mr. <hi>De Louvois</hi> directs him to purſue his undertaking, and after the Inſtitution of a judicial Court for the Examining of ſuch pretenſions which the King of <hi>France</hi> might have to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Territories and Principalities; Mr. Solicitor for his pains was nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated of that Court Judge in chief which is no more than ſetting the concern'd party in the Cauſe upon the Bench.</p>
            <p>I know not if I have exſpatiated a little too far upon the ſubject, but I thought it an incumbent upon me to report here the Original cauſes of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:205236:17"/>Miſeries which afflict us, and ready now to involve ſo many States in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and confuſion.</p>
            <p>We revert then to where we left, which as I take it was, the King of <hi>France</hi> not caring greatly for his <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> Alliance, Summons that Crown to do him Fealty and Homage for the Dukedome of <hi>Deux-ponts:</hi> The King of <hi>Swede</hi> being a young Prince, brave, and inferior to none in Reſolution and courage, thought the Chimerical pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention very ſtrange, but not willing to fall out with <hi>France</hi> upon a frivolous Matter, his Ambaſſador had Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to ſhew that King the injuſtice done him. That the Dukedom of <hi>Deux-ponts</hi> had ever been a Sovereign State, and that they who had it acknowledg'd Fealty and Homage for it to no Man living, except they meant for a Fealty and Homage, the uſual inveſtures they were obliged to take at the hands of the Emperor.</p>
            <p>Theſe Reaſons the Court of <hi>France</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd not of, proceeding on ſtill in her
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:205236:18"/>unjuſt demands of a Homage, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a canvas paſt of <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> between the Ambaſſadors and Miniſters, the new Court of Juſtice pronounces round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decree of Re-union, and that Dutchy to be annex't to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> unleſs within ſuch a ſet time the King of <hi>Swede</hi> acknowledged for the ſame his Fealty and Homage: Now that the World might ſee it was not from any covet of our Neighbours goods that Decree of <hi>Metz</hi> aris'd, the King freely offer'd the Inveſture of that Dukedom to the Duke <hi>Adolphus</hi> Uncle to the King of <hi>Swede</hi> in caſe the King his Nephew conform'd not to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure of the Decree which to be ſure he was not like to do.</p>
            <p>Whilſt Duke <hi>Adolphus</hi> halted between the hopes of getting that Dukedom and fear of diſobliging the King his Nephew the King of <hi>France</hi> ſends in the interim the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Bir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenfield,</hi> a Prince of the <hi>Palatine</hi> Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to keep that Dutchy in the Name of Duke <hi>Alfonſus</hi> his near Kinſman, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205236:18"/>in caſe that Duke accepted of it not upon the conditions propoſed him, he himſelf ſhould be then immediately inveſted; the Prince of <hi>Birkenfield</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving return'd his thanks for the Kings good will towards him, and having done him Fealty and Homage for the the Dukedom in name of Duke <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> he repair'd accordingly to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of his Commiſſion, I ſhall be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent here in reflecting upon the Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancys of this way of proceeding. A Reader does not ſo much care to have the point decided to his hand, 'tis limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Fancy, and by reaſoning firſt upon the ſubject, but giving Laws to his Faith in what he ſhould believe: And indeed 'tis as much as is requiſite for the Relator to tell of things as they nakedly are, and for the Reader to judge as he thinks good: But to cloſe the ſmall digreſſion not unſeaſonable to the profeſſion of Writers, the King of <hi>Swede</hi> had no ſooner heard what had been tranſacted in <hi>France,</hi> but upon it immediately deſerted the Alliance he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:205236:19"/>had embrac't during the late Wars at the hazard of his whole Country, and peril of his Life, having expoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the firſt Man in Perſon, in Three or Four ſeveral Battels for the ſake and intereſt of that Crown, expecting ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind of uſage for his pains from <hi>France</hi> then that he met with: <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> and <hi>Brandenburg</hi> no ſooner well aſſur'd what ſide the King of <hi>Swede</hi> would take, but both ſtrike up with <hi>France,</hi> which had engaged to furniſh the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> both with Ships and Men for the recovery not only of ſome Provinces which the Father of this King of <hi>Swede</hi> had taken from the <hi>Dane,</hi> but likewiſe for that of <hi>Lubeck,</hi> upon which City by vertue of ſome imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Titles <hi>Denmark</hi> of long hand had great Deſigns: <hi>Brandenburg</hi> did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to himſelf too a beneficial Alliance; inſomuch as theſe Three Potentates united but to the breeding a diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in the Northern Peace: <hi>France</hi> having thus made ſure of theſe two lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Staffs, by Vertue of the like De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:205236:19"/>I now mention'd, proceeds in the ſame way againſt other Sovereign Princes, requiring of them the ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Fealty and Homage: Many who ſaw themſelves not in condition to reſiſt acquieſc'd in all they would demand, others ſhew'd themſelves more ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, but ſmarted for their ſtanding out by the Quartering, and Gariſoning their Country, forc't by fowl means, to do what by fair they had refuſed. But here I muſt give account what happen'd to the <hi>Rinegrave,</hi> his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Country being great, and his example of influence to others, <hi>France</hi> let him underſtand he had to comply immediately without a boggle, and that after they would replace him again in all his Rights &amp; Priviledges: The <hi>Rinegrave</hi> not ſuſpecting the honorable Word of ſo auguſt a Crown was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd to be ſo advantageouſly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht among ſo many unfortunate ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers, and having given his Obedience wrought in others the ſame acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, which as they thought was
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:205236:20"/>unavoidable, having without ſo much as heſitating ſeen the <hi>Rinegrave</hi> Count per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the like ſubmiſſions, but when the Count on his ſide expected they ſhould keep their Word with him, was told they were not the Maſters, and that he muſt make his Applications to the Court, thither then muſt he take a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney &amp; little to the purpoſe, for inſtead of gaining the thing he made demand of, they e'en told him he might go as he came, and wonder'd in their Hearts ſuch a petty Fellow as he ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to hold his Country in Fee of ſo great a King as was the great King of <hi>France:</hi> A little before ſuch another Anſwer had been made to the <hi>Palatine</hi> Elector who ſending to the Court of <hi>France</hi> to complain of his Country be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made daily havoc of by the Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs of the <hi>French</hi> Forces, to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringement of the late Peace, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainer was anſwer'd when a little Prince like that Elector had the Honour to be Neighbour to ſo great a King 'twas not for ſuch as he to be that nice:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:205236:20"/>Short and ſweet this, hitherto Roſes; but in concluſion we ſhall have Thorn and all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> ſtill claims on their right of Dependencys, and finding <hi>Spain</hi> weak &amp; apparently helpleſs, the County of <hi>Aloſt</hi> is demanded of them as an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertenance of the late Conqueſts; <hi>Spain</hi> troubled at the demand, becauſe <hi>Ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermond</hi> with other Towns and Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges did all belong to the ſame County, let <hi>France</hi> underſtand the great Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of her pretended right, but whilſt this was under debate between the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Embaſſador and the Miniſters they yet made more demands as intricate all out and as perplext as their firſt: The County of <hi>Chini</hi> had been granted <hi>France</hi> by the Tenure of the Treaty with all its appertenancies, and as thoſe Dependancies had not receiv'd their full Explanation in the wording of the Peace, <hi>France</hi> now become what <hi>Spain</hi> did uſe to be, to ſay, a wrangler, and full of her fetches, and quibling tricks, alledged the Dependancies of <hi>Chini</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:205236:21"/>reacht to the very Gates of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> and therefore requir'd to have poſſeſſion thereof given them by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> if not they would give it themſelves: The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Embaſſador as very able Man as he was, was puzzled at the new quiddity, and demanded time to make his Maſter acquainted; the time he ask't was granted him, but when ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pir'd, <hi>France</hi> finding <hi>Spain</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to elude its pretenſions cauſes Forces openly to march into the Country of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> blocks up all the High-ways that lead to the County, Town, raiſes Forts round about, and tho then in the midſt of a profound Peace, commits all the acts of an actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Hoſtility which could poſſibly be committed in a declar'd War; the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> ſends his Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet to the Commander in chief of thoſe Forces to know if <hi>France</hi> mean'd a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of a War with <hi>Spain:</hi> But he was anſwer'd they meant no ſuch thing, and that they only were about taking poſſeſſion of what belong'd to them.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205236:21"/>Mean while under the Notion of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion-taking they hindred every thing from coming into the Town of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> and every thing from going out on't, and if any offer'd to paſs their way, they ſent them back to the Town again, pretending they came out as Spies upon their actions, and if there came any from the Country, ſuch as their Market-people, or the like with Proviſions to ſell in Town as they were us'd to do, they ſent them back too, having firſt ſtrip't them of all they had, to teach them not to come again a ſecond time, and if thoſe Country People offer'd to paſs them without Proviſions were ſuffer'd to go by after a due Examine of all they had about them, but when they would repaſs home again, were drove back into the Town, that ſo the Proviſions of the Place might be conſumed the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>When for my part, I reflect upon theſe violent Courſes I could not but be extreamly ſurpriz'd to ſee <hi>England</hi> the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:205236:22"/>Mediator and Garanty of the Peace, troubled themſelves no further in its due execution, they ſaw before their Eyes what paſs'd, but without the leaſt concern for the viſible infraction; and as if <hi>France</hi> had made all ſure upon that hand, purſued in their conſtant and daily acts of open Hoſtility; but yet offer'd ſtill to make <hi>England</hi> the Umpire of their debate, which left <hi>Spain</hi> without all ſort of hope; for upon one ſide not having confidence enough in <hi>England</hi> to truſt its Intereſt in their hands, upon t'other knew not what well to ſay to the King of <hi>France</hi> ſo fairly offering to refer the Matter: Perplext on both hands, <hi>Spain</hi> reſolves to put ſomething to the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a chance, and ſeeing the Town of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> muſt apparently be loſt for want of Proviſions ſent the Governour of the place private Orders to open a paſſage by force come what will: The Governour who for a long time deſir'd no better, ſallies out at a time when the <hi>French</hi> leaſt expected him, and ſetting
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:205236:22"/>upon one of their Quarters, charged them home as they juſt were upon the point of making head to diſpute the paſſage: The <hi>French</hi> made a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, but over-power'd by number, being forc't to give way, the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour advancing and joining his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy which he of long hand held before in a readineſs, put his relief into the Town. Some two hundred of the <hi>French</hi> were killed in the action, and about Eighteen or Twenty of the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> but among all theſe not a Man of note loſt, nor ſo much as one Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> no ſooner had the News, but thunder'd it againſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> as much indeed to blame they quietly would not endure ſtarving: Drew eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where preſently their Forces down towards the Towns that held for <hi>Spain,</hi> but at the inſtant of acting with them, <hi>England</hi> hinder'd from further procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by making <hi>France</hi> get full ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the point from <hi>Spain,</hi> who diſown'd not only all the Governor of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:205236:23"/>
               <hi>Luxemburg</hi> had done, but offering even to diſcharge him of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in ſhort ſo ſupinely weak, paid for the Damage in concluſion ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain'd by the <hi>French,</hi> for a certain Sum of Money agreed upon. After this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate Treaty, the <hi>Blocus</hi> of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> was afreſh begun again, and the <hi>French</hi> reinforc't their Quarter, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trol'd the Avenues duly for their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſecurity of being in haſte catcht as they before had been: Truly I can't contain from a little digreſſion here, and ſay Poſterity will be hardly made believe that in the mid'ſt of Peace, the one ſide ſhall be allow'd them to make War, but the other ſhall be puniſht be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſubmit not in every thing their Enemies would impoſe upon them. Howbeit the <hi>Luxemburg</hi> Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon being large, and the Convoy not ſufficient for a long ſupply began again to feel the ſame inconveniences it had before: The Governour being a brave Man, who had much rather have choſe to die with his Arms in his Hand, then
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:205236:23"/>lead out a life ſo very ſhameful and ſo unworthy of any Man of Courage, was for all that neceſſitated to bear with a Thouſand of their Inſolencies, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults without the leaſt daring to gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay: For the <hi>French</hi> who well knew his Inſtructions, and whoſe Fingers itcht to be doing, would frequently come within half a Mile ſight of the Town, where having trodden down the Corn under their Horſes feet made ſhew of a defying to engage. Whil'ſt this was doing <hi>France</hi> Treats for <hi>Cazal,</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Mantoua,</hi> which threw not a little Jealouſie <hi>Italy</hi> all over: The Emperor too reſented it in a high meaſure for <hi>Cazal;</hi> beſides, being a Feif of the Empire, he was by deſcent too the preſumptive Heir, and ſo doubly intitled as Emperor, and the next near Kinſman to the Duke of <hi>Mantoua:</hi> It was not to be expected, the King of <hi>France</hi> would ſo much leſſen himſelf to be ſending to the Emperor, to demand inveſture as was cuſtomary to be done for all Feifs of the Empire, he was not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:205236:24"/>a Prince to be preſcrib'd the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of ordinary rules, and his uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolable power freed him in every thing; which indeed Mr. Solicitor Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Court of <hi>Metz,</hi> of whom I have before ſpoken, did ingenuouſly confeſs as much one day, to ſome of his Friends ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king freedom to be telling him they did not conceive the ſtrength of his Decrees was of validity ſufficient to be binding in the caſe of ſo many Sovereign Princes: Reply'd he ſerv'd a Maſter who had at beck, a Hundred pieces of <hi>Canon,</hi> a Hundred thouſand Men, and a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Millions of Money to put thoſe Decrees in Execution. The Taking of <hi>Cazal</hi> was not the only thing <hi>Italy</hi> was alarm'd at, <hi>France,</hi> whoſe ambition nothing leſs then the ſubjection of the whole World could ſatisfie, began now to grumble too at the Republic of <hi>Genoua,</hi> to have that colour of invading its liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: They of <hi>Genoua</hi> ſend their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador to <hi>France</hi> at the ſame time, to excuſe themſelves in what they could, but as <hi>France</hi> was not without her Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:205236:24"/>I mean good or bad, the Excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the poor <hi>Genoeſſes</hi> were ill recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved, took the occaſion to pick a New quarrel in requiring them to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of an Eſtate formerly of the Houſe of <hi>Fieske,</hi> with the Intereſt of the whole for an Age before ſince ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crued; now as every Body is well ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied what the caſe of the Houſe of <hi>Fieske</hi> is, and how they were, and for what expell'd <hi>Genoua</hi> would be here ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to mention: I ſhall but ſay, never Demand appear'd more extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry then that did, not to ſay never a more unjuſt, and a more unreaſonable. <hi>France</hi> would oblige a Gree State to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore to the Heirs and Succeſſors of a Traitor, and Eſtate forfeited and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated for its delinquency, as if <hi>France</hi> never had her ſelf confiſcated, and daily did not confiſcate Eſtates of ſuch as ſhe found faulty, and deficient in their duty: Mean while though the Matter has not been drove much further, 'tis not to be imagin'd notwithſtanding wholly laid aſide, 'tis a ſmothering Fire in Aſhes,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:205236:25"/>which one day will conſume all <hi>Italy,</hi> if not prevented by the Hand of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and indeed 'tis not to be thought <hi>France</hi> has quitted therefore the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of maſtering that Common-wealth, becauſe ſhe defers the doing it to another time, for that the preſent was of more conſequence to be looking to the Conqueſt of <hi>Flanders</hi> which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto had been ſo tedious a work, and now lay naked and expoſed to his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition through the unfortunate diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Imperial Arms: 'Twas then ill Policy to draw ſo many Enemies upon her Hands at once, whoſe Buſineſs ſhe the eaſier might all do, the one after the other: 'Twas an advice worth ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king which a grand Politician once gave his Children upon the point of Death, caus'd a great many arrows to be laid before them, ſome of which in bundle, others loſe, and bid the Children to try the breaking of thoſe unbound, which they eaſily ſnap't in two, then commanded them to try the other, bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them to break thoſe likewiſe,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:205236:25"/>but that being more then they were able, took his occaſion from that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to admoniſh them to remain ever in Union with one another, if they expected their Enemies ſhould take no hold upon them. Now <hi>France</hi> deals with moſt of the other Princes, as the Children by thoſe Arrows not bound to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſhe eaſily ſubdues them one after another, which in caſe they were linkt, and united as they ſhould be, might perhaps be in a poſture of reducing her again within the bounds of Reaſon: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed what hinders the ſetting Armies upon foot as well as <hi>France,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by an endeavor uſed for the reſettling of things in that condition again, where every one concern'd might find his ſecurity.</p>
            <p>It looks as if our Fore-Fathers were much the prudenter People: For I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member well after the Battel of <hi>Pavie,</hi> where <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth Triumph't over the Affairs and Fortune of <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, they wiſely conſider'd not fit to ſuffer any more the growth and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:205236:26"/>mightineſs of that Power, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready was become but too formidable among them, and ſo retrieved again the State of <hi>France</hi> at that time much more deſperate, &amp; at a lower Ebb then is ours now. But 'tis not for want of every Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies knowing what courſe was taken in the times of our Anceſtors, but few they be make a true uſe of what they know.</p>
            <p>But all this while, I perceive not my deviation inſenſibly ſtealing me from my Subject, too far carried off by force of Truth: To come then to the point again, I ſhall tell you, that whilſt <hi>Italy</hi> took the alarm at the ſurrender of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zal,</hi> another buſineſs was then brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that Country, which might well occaſion its further diſturbance. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> as every one knows, lies cloſed up between <hi>France</hi> on one ſide, and the Provinces of <hi>Spain:</hi> I mean between thoſe Countrys in <hi>Italy</hi> under <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Dominion: The Neighbourhood of theſe two Powers has been Reaſon enough in all former Ages, why the Dukes of <hi>Savoy</hi> enjoy little quiet: For
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:205236:26"/>at the ſame time that either of thoſe two Crowns denounced War upon the other, he muſt of neceſſity ſide with one of the two, to prevent his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try from being over-run by both, as is the general caſe of all Neuters. Now as <hi>Savoy</hi> turn'd very much the Scale to the ſide it inclin'd to, the two Crowns ſtrove their utmoſt which ſhould have him of their party, that ſometimes the Daughters of <hi>France,</hi> ſometimes the Infanta's of <hi>Spain</hi> found Wives of State for that Duke, and the need both had of him, was ſtill the <hi>Mediums</hi> of new advantages from either: <hi>France</hi> who knew at what dear rates that Alliance was ſometimes to be purchas'd, proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a Treaty with him, ſuch as for ever ſhould debar him from being <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> any more. The Cardinal <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrée</hi> they ſend to <hi>Savoy,</hi> a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Dutcheſs, and as ſhe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd all during the Minority of her Son, propoſes to her a Match between the young Duke, and the Infanta of <hi>Portugal,</hi> his Couſin German, Heir pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:205236:27"/>of that Crown, the then Prince Regent having no more Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: The Dutcheſs of <hi>Savoy</hi> being Born in <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>French</hi> in all her Inclinations reliſhes the Propoſal with pleaſure: Thinking the Quality of a King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> was every whit Equivalent to a Duke of <hi>Savoy:</hi> But as they have a Law in <hi>Portugal,</hi> which Forfeits in a Daughter her right of Succeſſion to the Crown in caſe of Marriage with a Stranger, that Law how to aboliſh muſt firſt be thought of; The Cardinal <hi>Deſtrée</hi> in Name of his Maſter undertook the thing: <hi>France</hi> ſends then to <hi>Portugal</hi> to that effect, and as ſhe was in a happy poſt of carrying all before her, did in that conjuncture too carry that Affair, inſomuch as the having of that Law abrogated, and the Dukes Marriage with their Infanta fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally agreed upon: The Grandees of <hi>Savoy,</hi> without whoſe advice this Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs had been determin'd unſatisfied with the Match, which ended in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privement of their natural Prince, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:205236:27"/>the Subordination of a Governour, had their private Cabals to conſult the breaking the Neck of the Marriage, and ſtop it from further going on. I cannot juſtly ſay, if they confederated for ſake of public good, or meerly for their private ends; howbeit the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal</hi> Match far from being of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the Duke, one may truly ſay he was a loſer by the Bargain, no leſs then the Princes in general of his Family; beſides, whilſt he was to have reſided in <hi>Portugal</hi> who ſhould have ſuccor'd <hi>Savoy,</hi> in caſe <hi>France</hi> had had a mind to ſet up right of Conveniency, a right which they endeavor'd equally to eſtabliſh as well as right of Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, and for no other Reaſon indeed was the Prince of <hi>Montbelliard</hi> drove out of his Country then that it did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate the Crown: But they hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded little all that could be ſaid againſt it, and ſtill went on their Road, where but a glimpſe appear'd of probable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſceſs: Madam, the Dutches of <hi>Savoy</hi> ſmoakt the drift, as well as any, but
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:205236:28"/>the powerful deſire of Sovereign Rule, carried it above all other conſiderations; and as <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Farneſe,</hi> Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> ſent off his Mother in former days, not to be oblig'd to ſhare with her the Government of the Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: So the Dutcheſs of <hi>Savoy</hi> was for packing away her Son, that ſhe might remain ſtill the abſolute Miſtreſs of that State: She knew well enough they would not fail detaining the Duke in <hi>Portugal</hi> to inure him to the ways and cuſtoms of a Nation which one day he was deſign'd to govern; and by the ſhift ſecure to her ſelf the Supreme Authority: In the mean while diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents amongſt the Grandees encreas'd daily, and have frequent meetings to adviſe upon what they had to do; could not for all that meet ſo in private, but the Dutcheſs had Intelligence, willing to ſecure her ſelf from the Deſigns her Grandees might well have of troubling the Government, cauſed Forces to be fetcht from <hi>France</hi> in good ſtore to be diſpers'd in the Neigbourhood about,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:205236:28"/>under a pretence of covering <hi>Cazal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Nobility of <hi>Savoy,</hi> though alarm'd at the <hi>French</hi> aſſiſting thus of the Dutcheſs, gave not over for all that their Intentions of helping their young Duke, and having found her out in her Treaty with <hi>France,</hi> into whoſe hands ſhe had agreed to deliver the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant places of ſtrength in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in Pledge of ſome Loans of Money ſhe had borrow'd of them, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fray of her Son's Marriage, were una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly reſolv'd to hazard all than ſuffer thus a general ruine; and as they watch't their opportunity to compaſs their deſign, the Dutcheſs her ſelf favour'd them with one, which they conceiv'd might ſerve their turn, for having left her Son at <hi>Turin,</hi> contrary to her cuſtom, whilſt her ſelf ſtept a Mile or two out of Town, the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, took that Time to ſpeak to their Duke: That he muſt look upon himſelf in <hi>French</hi> hands, every where ſurrounding him as now their Priſoner in a manner, that the Dutcheſs his Mother had ſold
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:205236:29"/>them his beſt Towns, and would yet be ſelling what remain'd if not preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his great goodneſs to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: That ſhe ſent him to <hi>Portugal</hi> not to be the Soveraign there, but that at home ſhe might be ſo: That in caſe he met with freedom to his Perſon there, he muſt at leaſt expect to meet a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, whereas if he vouchſafed to ſtay with them, he ſhould meet with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but their entire obedience and dutiful reſpects, that the <hi>Portuguiſes</hi> naturally hated Strangers; and if they did aſſent to his marrying their Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, 'twas by conſtraint, and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret: That he might reſt aſſur'd the Prince Regent once dead, they would retract again from what they had done, and bar him of his Crown as formerly they had done to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> that it was not eaſie to foreſee what might then become of him, for that the <hi>French</hi> having once ſeized his Country perhaps might not be in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor to reſtore it him again.</p>
            <p>Theſe remonſtrances ſtartled the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:205236:29"/>young Duke, who yet had not Brains ripe enough to apprehend among a great many Truths they repreſented, there was Lies in an equal number, he ask't them what beſt for him to act to ſhun ſo many threatning misfortunes: They anſwer'd no other way left, then the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of his Mother; the expedient was ſurprizing, but finding they had ſtruck from the firſt an impreſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the young Prince, gave him no time to the recollections of a Natural affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, preſt him with telling his own ſafety lay for the future in his own power, to reſolve for good and all of being a happy or unhappy Duke the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his life; as for their parts reſolv'd to be the lookers on of what every Day produced no longer, had deſign'd retiring into ſome other Country, where at leaſt they ſhould gain that comfort of Knowing they had no kind of Hand in any thing that would be attempted againſt his Dignity or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. A few Tears artificially ſhed, or out of compaſſionate good Nature,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:205236:30"/>accompliſht perſuading of the Duke, calls for Pen and Paper, and ſigns a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant immediately for the ſeizing of his Mother: In the mean while before they could get together to take their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for execution of their Order, the Dutcheſs was return'd into the Town, and being arriv'd at her <hi>Palais</hi> was extremely ſurprized to find her Son ſad and penſive, and much beſide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, askt what he ail'd, conjuring him to tell her, but finding him not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, ſhe adds to her entreaties the blandiſhments of a Mother, as ſhe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced him, perceiv'd he wep't, and Tears to tricle down his Cheeks which troubled her to the higheſt degree, ſell then to a redoublement of muching, calls him her own deareſt Child, falls her ſelf a crying, and in the end ſo ſoftens, he confeſſes to her they had ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized him, and that he had ſigned an Order for the commitment of her Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: The Dutcheſs was her ſelf ſtruck with amaze at the ſort of News, but having now no time to loſe, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:205236:30"/>that every Minut was to her of higheſt conſequence, ſent for thoſe about her immediately ſhe could moſt confide in, doubles the Palace Guards, and cauſes thoſe to be ſeiz'd in fine who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd her ruine &amp; makes her <hi>manifeſto,</hi> thoſe very Perſons were intended to take away the young Duke, and carry him to <hi>Spain,</hi> which is more then I can ſay they meant, not knowing whether true or not, or whether only a Sham to render them the more odious to the People: Be it as 'twill, the Dutcheſs having once retriev'd her ſelf from ſo very great a danger, order'd the <hi>French</hi> Forces to March into the Town thereby to ſhew ſhe truſted more to them, then to thoſe of the Country.</p>
            <p>A certain Print for all this remain'd with the young Duke of what had been remonſtrated; inſomuch that though his Equipage was gone already before to <hi>Portugal,</hi> and himſelf ſoon to follow after, he talk't no more of the Voyage: And as ſtill ſome body there was in place about him, who privately che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:205236:31"/>the ſuſpicion they had rais'd, broke him clean off, order'd his Family to return their ways home again, to the unſpeakable ſatisfaction of his whole People; <hi>France</hi> only remain'd much mortifid, promiſing already to it ſelf the conjunction of <hi>Savoy</hi> to that Kingdom, and to enchaſe it amongſt the faireſt Flowers of the Crown: The diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction conceiv'd lay not long hid, the Count of <hi>Soiſſon</hi> who in caſe of deceaſe of the young Duke was Heir preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to the Dukedom of <hi>Savoy,</hi> after the Death of Prince <hi>Carignan</hi> his Uncle, was then in love with a private Damo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel in <hi>France,</hi> call'd <hi>Madamoſeille de Beauais;</hi> all the Relations had thither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to oppoſed the thing, in fear of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to marry her, the King himſelf had ſignifi'd as much, and that he ought to think of beſtowing himſelf ſome other way, but being thus diſoblig'd by the Grandees of <hi>Savoy,</hi> he ſuffer'd Count <hi>Soiſſon</hi> to do what he had moſt mind to, to humble him, and that Count did do what his paſſion perſuaded.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:205236:31"/>
            <p>This what paſt in <hi>Piemont,</hi> let us now go ſee a little what a doing in <hi>Germany; France</hi> for a long time had a Months mind to the City of <hi>Straſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> it had defeated them a number of its meaſures during the late War, and <hi>France</hi> had ſo well felt the importance of that place to reſolve upon the having it, coſt it ne're ſo much: To ſpeak of having it by force, lookt a little dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, and to do that a War muſt be openly declar'd, and the adjacent Princes round about would have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in her defence. The eaſier way then ſeem'd the getting it by trick: A Reſident they kept at <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> in Character more of Spy then public Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, whoſe Buſineſs was to obſerve all that paſt; he had given the King often times account no good was to be done till thoſe Burgemaſters of the Town in preſent ſtation were out of place, when new came to be made, had by that time gain'd a great many of the Votes, got Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons elected to the Magiſtracy affection'd to the Intereſts of <hi>France,</hi> ready fitted to make ſale of their Country for a piece of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:205236:32"/>Money, with theſe after that, he ſtrikes a Bargain for the delivery of the Town upon the firſt occaſion, and they for their Reward to have each a Hundred Thouſand Crowns a Man. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket being thus ſet, theſe Traytors give the Town to conſider the great Burthens of their Debt they ſtood charg'd with occaſion'd by her vaſt Expences incurr'd in the late War, and that now in time of Peace they ſhould reduce the Gariſon which was too nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous: That the King of <hi>France,</hi> whom they had the moſt cauſe to fear, had his whole thoughts took up towards <hi>Italy,</hi> whither he had drawn the beſt part of all his Forces, and that before he could march them back again they ſhould have time enough to implore the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of their Neighbours, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per concern in their preſervation was too great not to afford them aid; hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen what would they had the Winter before to look about them, which was now at hand: That the King was great way diſtant from them, as indeed he was, and Summer then near ſpent,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:205236:32"/>there was no manner of likelihood, he durſt undertake any thing actually that ſeaſon, &amp; by the means ſave a good Sum of Money in their Purſes; that when Spring time came, they then ſhould ſee what other meaſures were fitteſt to be taken.</p>
            <p>The advice took with the People, who were all for the ſparing point, and for all the ableſt men amongſt them could formally oppoſe what the People once would have of neceſſity to be, there was no withſtanding, one part of the Gariſon muſt then be diſmiſt, and which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable of thoſe the Forces of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſtanding: But as the King of <hi>France</hi> lay perdue, but for the occaſion, took Journey forthwith from <hi>Fountain-bleau</hi> at the ſame time caus'd his Men to draw down with expedition and inveſts the City, at a time they imagin'd him in the midſt of his Kingdom. Some play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Cannon there was upon both ſides, to take off all ſuſpicion off In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, which hinder'd not, but thoſe of <hi>Strasburgh</hi> well enough un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood themſelves betray'd. And tho
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:205236:33"/>they now underſtood ſo with the lateſt, they yet entertain'd thoughts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Defence: But a rable of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hired at the ſame time by the <hi>French</hi> Reſident, or it may be as well by the Burgemaſters themſelves came flocking to the Town-houſe, crying out for a ſurrender of the Town, which otherwiſe would be ſuddenly conſum'd by the Fire of the Booms, and by the red hot Bullets. The Burgemaſters ſoon liſtn'd to that demand, cauſe beat a Parly, ſet up the White Colours for token of a general readineſs to capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and in a word to ſay all, yields up the Town.</p>
            <p>I do not condemn <hi>France,</hi> for an act of this importance, ſince not of humor to matter much her Faith in point of Treaty; but what I am moſt ſcandal'd at, to have the Face to colour it with a ſhew of Juſtice. The Emperor indeed having ſent Count <hi>Mansfeld</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the Breach of Peace, was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd that they much wonder'd the Emperor would concern himſelf, where
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:205236:33"/>he had not to do, that it was but lawful for the King to reduce a rebellious City: That <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> as the Capital of <hi>Alſace</hi> did belong to him, by Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the <hi>Munſter</hi> Treaty, and if he did not lay hold on't ſooner 'twas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had more preſſing work in Hand: But any would but anſwer me, if that City had been granted him as pretended, why entertain'd he there his public Miniſters ſo long time, why did he in the laſt War treat with her in Order to her remaining Neuter, and why ſo often complaining of her not remaining ſo? But all that <hi>France</hi> can ſay upon the ſubject, is indeed not ſo much as worth an anſwer, &amp; ſo I proceed to her Enterprizes elſewhere: The taking of <hi>Strasburgh</hi> open'd the Eyes of a great many <hi>German</hi> Princes, lull'd for a long time like <hi>England</hi> in a profound Sleep. Every one was for revenging the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but when they came to act accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there was none but met with a Difficulty and Lyon in the way, one had no Money to begin a War, another
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:205236:34"/>for not hazarding his Men, which he reſerv'd for ſome other time, another he would firſt know, to whom the Town ſhould fall when retaken; in ſhort, if any ſeem'd to be accorded together 'twas but as they conſpir'd each by their mutual ill conducts in the twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of Cords for their own Bondage. In the mean while <hi>France</hi> loſt not her good time thus in unuſeful Diſcourſes: During the laſt War had all along kept a correſpondence with <hi>Teckely,</hi> by the help of one <hi>Bohan</hi> of <hi>Ardenn</hi> by Nation, and whom I remember to have ſeen a Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of Horſe in the <hi>French</hi> Army. He afterwards was in Service with the <hi>Pole,</hi> but being reform'd upon the Peace made between the Port and that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, went to ſeek his Fortune with <hi>Tecke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> who took care to advance him, for that beſides being a Man of good parts, was very likely to make a good Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer; ſome three or four years ſince he had been in <hi>France,</hi> diſcours'd the Miniſters, &amp; ſetled there correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with them, that being call'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:205236:34"/>to make good his Word he had given them, order'd ſo his matters, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent their expectations, and to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; <hi>Teckely</hi> engages to give diverſion in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and that he might be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in condition to bring in the <hi>Turks,</hi> has granted him great ſupplies of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and far greater promis'd him, if once able to put in execution, the thing he had undertaken.</p>
            <p>This Buſineſs has been ſo generally known, that 'tis not to be doubted, by any who have had the leaſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of what paſſes in the World: Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters went from <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Germany,</hi> from <hi>Germany</hi> to <hi>Bohan</hi> by the means of a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary, to a certain Envoy the King there entertain'd, and from <hi>Bohan</hi> to <hi>Teckely:</hi> The Secretary lay long by the heels for this Buſineſs, and had not the King of <hi>France</hi> clapt up Count <hi>Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld</hi>'s Secretary in requital, he had not been freed upon ſo eaſie a reckoning; but he being committed to the <hi>Baſtille,</hi> and told he might be ſure to have the ſame uſage, whatever the other had at
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:205236:35"/>the hands of the Emperor, oblig'd him quickly to poſt ſome a way to <hi>Vienna</hi> to give notice: The Emperor upon that ſtopt any further proceedings, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſe to forgive the Guilty, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Innocent; yet to let ſee how ſenſible he was of the Injury, had the Priſoner let looſe, but at <hi>Briſac,</hi> where for the greater Marks of Infamy he was brought upon a Cart, bolted with Irons Hand and Foot, and under Guard ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient; 'twas fear'd <hi>France</hi> provoked by the Treatment, might do as much to Count <hi>Mansfeld</hi>'s Secretary; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of a better knowledge of her ſelf, or that ſhe fear'd offering violence to the Right of Nations, of which I muſt needs ſay ſhe is a moſt Religious Obſerver, he was let go out of the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtille,</hi> without uſing of any Repriſals in the caſe, and even ſuffer'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in <hi>Paris,</hi> where I have been told he yet remains.</p>
            <p>The Mighty Huff that follow'd after the taking of <hi>Strasburgh</hi> being vaniſht into Air: <hi>France</hi> as I ſaid before, whoſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:205236:35"/>Stomach ſtill mended at the ſight of a freſh Diſh, began again in Right of her Dependencies, which in proportion to her greedy Belly ſhe extended, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand one part of <hi>Liege,</hi> even to the Moity of its Capital City, mean while as a Country frontier to <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> as well as the Low-Countries, and for the deſigns ſhe had on both it was expedient for her purpoſe to meet with no reſiſtance, ſhe had during the late Wars, thrown down all the Forts, and diſmantled the Walls, already was in poſſeſſion of the Caſtle of <hi>Dinan,</hi> by force of an Article in the <hi>Nemiguen</hi> Treaty by which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Obligation to procure them the Propriety of from the Elector of <hi>Cullen,</hi> Prince and Biſhop of <hi>Liege,</hi> to whom it of Right pertain'd, and the ſame to get ratifi'd at the Diet of <hi>Ratisbonne,</hi> or otherwiſe to give them <hi>Charlemont</hi> in ſtead. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> not able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with the Biſhop of <hi>Cullen,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the place from off his Country, or rather <hi>France</hi> having underhand
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:205236:36"/>hinder'd him from diſmembring to have always pretext in hand to be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the poor <hi>Spaniard</hi> with, when they ſo pleas'd: Beſides, the Diet of the Empire would conſent to no ſuch alienation; <hi>France</hi> finding all theſe obſtacles lay daily preſſing of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> to put <hi>Charlemont</hi> into their Hands, according to the Tenure of the Treaty; the <hi>Spaniards</hi> they hung back all they could, as if they had foreſeen what would come on't. But at laſt ſeeing <hi>France,</hi> who well knew how to make her uſe of the miſunderſtandings of one and t'other, threatned to fall downright upon <hi>Flanders</hi> if they made not good their Engagements, <hi>Charlemont</hi> was deliver'd, which is one of the beſt places <hi>France</hi> is this day in poſſeſſion of, though poſſeſſing of a great many good ones. When once <hi>Charlemont</hi> was in their Hands, the redelivering of <hi>Dinan,</hi> was no more mention'd, and ſo blocks up <hi>Namur</hi> by the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> that when ſhe pleaſes, can hinder any thing from coming
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:205236:36"/>to it by Water carriage: For as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs of the whole <hi>Liege</hi> Country, I know not which way <hi>Namur</hi> can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive relief, but on the Land ſide. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> might complain their Heart out of being thus dealt with <hi>France,</hi> was ne're the more concern'd, but the contrary, the firſt to cry out, The <hi>Spaniards</hi> had not perform'd to them their Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> ſince as yet they could not oblige them to a rendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the County of <hi>Aloſt,</hi> which of Right did to them belong.</p>
            <p>All the Electors, bordering upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> had a Crow to pull with <hi>France,</hi> about her Right of Dependance by the help of it pretending to ſwallow all places that lay commodious for her pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but when the thing demanded was had, or indeed the thing ſhe would give her ſelf, like the Fire which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conſum'd all near to it inſenſibly ſpreads it ſelf to places more remote, ſo ſhe having laid her clutches upon an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Tract of Country puſhes on her deſigns upon the very Capital
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:205236:37"/>Towns of the Electoral Princes; to that effect alledg'd ſhe that the ground where ſtood the Stables be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Elector of <hi>Mayence</hi> did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain with all the <hi>Hame,</hi> Country Soil, remarkable for the excellent Rheniſh that there grows: Her pretentions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the City of <hi>Cullen,</hi> and upon that of <hi>Mayence,</hi> bounds not with ſo ſmall a Buſineſs; <hi>France</hi> maintain'd that as theſe two Cities were much encreas'd by length of time, all that had been built for Four or Five preceeding Ages; was built upon what was granted her by Vertue of the Treaty, that therefore the buildings muſt be demoliſht, and the City reſtrain'd again to its Antient limits, or the Proprietors of thoſe Houſes from thence forward to pay Allegiance to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Things thus acted by that King, nothing more could ſhew how extremely they were deceived who ſaid he aimed ſo much at having his Son choſe King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſo far was he from deſigning that he ſhould
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:205236:37"/>ever arrive at the Empire, that 'twas his Buſineſs to give it rather an abſolute overthrow; and ſo began firſt with the Electors, that for the future ſuch a thing as Emperor might be no more in Nature.</p>
            <p>The Emperor, the Princes of the Empire, the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and in fine, all thoſe of the Cordial Allies ſaw but too plain the tendency of all theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; but it ſeems ſuch was the Fate of <hi>Europe,</hi> whilſt they loſt whole years in deliberating about triffles, <hi>France</hi> brings them under in the mean while, and prepares their Chains, whoſe weight is known by none, but by thoſe they load: For in fine, her own Ancient Subjects, and thoſe very Men, who daily ſpend themſelves to the laſt drop of their Blood in aſſiſting them to compaſs their intentions meet with the ſame ſort of Treatment is mett to others, and to begin with thoſe who ſerve in their Armies muſt be underſtood are all obliged to make a profuſe Expence till
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:205236:38"/>their all be whole run out, when ſhe Knows they have nothing left them, they pick a Fob-quarrel as one may call it, are after all glad to take to an Hoſpital for the final recompence of Service. 'Tis for that end, has ſhe truly built, and that a moſt ſumptuous one, but which ſtands them not in no great matter of keeping, having laid hold on certain Lands which the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Devotion of ſome People had given towards the relief of Lepers, and converted to the uſe of that Hoſpital, but as thoſe Rents ſuffice not for the maintenance or at leaſt will have it ſo ſuppoſed, ſhe detains in her Hands a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Sum from both of the pay of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier and Officer, and that way makes them purchaſe their Places beforehand which each is very well pleaſed to do for that they are ſatisfied, thither they all muſt come and lay their Bones. And thoſe out of her Service have not a much better time on't, for though not oblig'd to ſo great an Expence as others are, they ſqueeſe them to little by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:205236:38"/>till they have ſqueezed out the laſt of what they have. And though they have continu'd ſome time in Peace, they have diminiſht nothing of their Taxes, ſo that their King is the only Gainer by the War, all beſides lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Franch</hi> County he has added to his Provinces with a great many more ſeveral Conqueſts, which have very much augmented his Revenue, which by his ſeveral new impoſitions he has greatly added to, readier to lay more on then to ſuppreſs the Old. Now if they who ſerve, and who ſerve him not have ſo much to ſuffer, there yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains another ſort of People in that State who certainly are yet much more to be pittied: I mean thoſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Religion, who muſt endure on all ſort of outragious violences, for tho they do not outright put them to death by the Hands of a Hangman, as they are daily made to periſh by little and little, their death is but the crueller in that it is the more languiſhing, and have
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:205236:39"/>for all that never given but Eminent proofs of their Fidelity and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and though when <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth came to the Crown did he deſert them, it came not into their Thoughts to do as much by him, which at that time had wholly ruin'd his Affairs; ſome time they did remain quiet, and enjoy'd the benefit of their Edicts, but juſt it was they who were the great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſhould too diſturb a company of poor unhappy wretches, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded for ever from all Marks of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and places of truſt, have this how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to comfort themſelves, that for their Religion 'tis that they ſuffer. Amongſt the many of all ſorts <hi>France</hi> thus undoes, whether within or without the Kingdom, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was the only, as one may ſay, that nos'd them. And though his power was no more then what the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Holland</hi> were pleaſed to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him, his great Heart was not ſo bounded, and was incomparably grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his Fortune, he never gave
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:205236:39"/>over remonſtrating to ſome, that rather they ſhould chooſe to periſh, then ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to Power ſo terribly dangerous, to other ſome the abſolute neceſſity of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againſt her: many things that Prince had retrencht himſelf to raiſe a Fund for the ſubſiſtance of ſome well deſerving Officers, which that State at making of the Peace had reform'd, that ſo through neceſſity of Bread, they might not be oblig'd to ſeek Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment elſewhere, and when he had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for them, might know where to find them. <hi>France</hi> which knew ſhe had in him an Enemy ſhe moſt of all fear'd, reſolv'd he ſhould feel in his Perſonal concerns, a touch of her Reſentment, not to ſay of her Injuſtice, his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality of <hi>Orange</hi> lies between <hi>Languedoc</hi> and <hi>Avignon,</hi> which as Sovereign of, he had enjoy'd, he, and his Predeceſſors from the time it paſt out of the Houſe of <hi>Chalon</hi> into that of <hi>Naſſaw.</hi> But that King who was for ſuffering no Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign in <hi>France,</hi> nor in <hi>Europe</hi> neither, beſides himſelf, had the Town of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:205236:40"/>
               <hi>Orange</hi> diſmantled; and the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> left without any reparation, what complaint ſoever at that time he made of it to the King never ſo Inſtant: But the King ſtopt not there in relation to his Affairs, for having reſolv'd to ſtrip him abſolutely of that Sovereignty, he makes the Dutcheſs of <hi>Nemours</hi> put in, who by colour of ſome fooliſh and idle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, had the Prince cited at Law to their Courts of Judicature, where not giving his appearance, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality of <hi>Orange</hi> was adjudg'd her; no body can, no more than I, tell upon what bottom that Decree could ground: For if by Vertue of ſome pretended old Entail from the Houſe of <hi>Chalon,</hi> to which they will ſay the Predeceſſors of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> did not comply with, as it is eaſie to give proof ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to the contrary, 'tis not without a likelihood of Truth to ſay, that tho Madam <hi>de Nemours</hi> could make out the Title, her time was laps'd in point of claim; for that by the Laws of that Kingdom, ſuch at leaſt as I have ſeen
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:205236:40"/>them in caſe of Cuſtom, the preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Thirty years Poſſeſſion was ſufficient to quiet a Title, and that the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> I mean, the Prince and his Predeceſſors together have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd for above a Hundred and fifty years: But whether this be ſo or not, it hinder'd not, but Madam <hi>de Nemours</hi> obtain'd her Decree, which tho has for all that been ſince revok't, in the mean while the Prince has ſent Mr. <hi>Hemſius</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> to ſhew the King the wrong done him: The <hi>States</hi> General upon their part have particularly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended that Affair to their Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour in <hi>France,</hi> but hitherto ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; and tho 'tis now ſix Months that Mr. <hi>Hemſius</hi> is working at it, it yet appears not to have made any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs; but let us paſs to ſome other matter, this being but trifle in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with what I have yet to ſay.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Poland</hi> had ever been a Friend of <hi>France,</hi> 'twas by her means he got the Crown which every foot was ſending him preſents, in token of her
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:205236:41"/>Friendſhip, had given him her Order of Holy Ghoſt, and the only Prince ſhe in fine, thought well of in <hi>Europe</hi> beſides. Now let us ſee how they came to break with him, and at whoſe Door lies the fault; 'tis indeed with difficulty I muſt diſcover this, but out it muſt being got ſo far there is no going back: The Money ſent by <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Teckely</hi> was no uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſupply, he had for it engag'd the <hi>Turks</hi> to fall upon the Emperor; and <hi>France</hi> having due Intelligence of all that paſt, both of time and place, and of the other ſide preferr'd the carrying on of her Intregues to all other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, made no Bones of Soliciting the King of <hi>Poland</hi> at that time to attack the Emperors Country upon his ſide, as the right of conveniency was an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive ſort of right in her Eyes, which ſway'd with her, imagin'd it might do the ſame with the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and propos'd to him the Conqueſt of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> where in probability he was not like to meet with any great reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the Moment the <hi>Ottoman</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:205236:41"/>Forces had made their deſcent into <hi>Hungary,</hi> the King of <hi>Poland</hi> who is a ſharp Prince, and who needs no prompters to teach him his Leſſon, thought it improper to his own Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as to that of his Crown, to make uſe of the advice, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, he accepts of an Alliance with the Emperor then propos'd him by which they mutually engaged by League Offenſive and Defenſive to aſſiſt each other againſt the <hi>Turk: France</hi> had no ſooner learnt what the King of <hi>Poland</hi> had done but her former Kindneſs was immediately chang'd into an irreconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable hate, ſends to the Marquis of <hi>Vitry</hi> her Ambaſſadour in that Court a Man of Parts, and good at an Intregue, to employ his skill to ſet all at work in creating miſunderſtandings betwixt him and his people, and <hi>Morſtein</hi> high Treaſurer of <hi>Poland,</hi> who was a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner of <hi>France,</hi> and where he had thoughts to ſettle himſelf, and where he already had purchas'd great poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, aſſiſts <hi>Vitry</hi> in his deſign; already
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:205236:42"/>had they tamper'd with ſome of the diſcontented Senators, who talk't at no lower rates then the obliging the King of <hi>Poland</hi> to relinquiſh the Government. For the purpoſe already caſt their Eyes upon a Perſon they had deſign'd the Throne to in his ſtead; When as good fortune would have it, the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> intercepted a Letter of <hi>Morſtein</hi>'s writ in Cyphers, he ſends for him forthwith, and having enquir'd of him the meaning of the Letter, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he endeavour'd to ſhift the Truth, bid him give the Key, <hi>Morſtein</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd 'twas with his Wite, which forc't the King to ſend for her, when ſhe came, and found for what the King had ſent for her, told, ſhe had burnt the Key, and not being able to get out any better account, commanded the Commitment of them both under a ſtrong Guard till he ſifted the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair a little more narrowly: I ſhall ſay no more upon this Chapter; every one knows the <hi>French</hi> Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador convinc'd of Tampering in the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:205236:42"/>Buſineſs, a certain Senator out of pure love to his King and Country was bold enough to ſay in full aſſembly, ſpeaking of <hi>Morſtan,</hi> that for attempts of a leſs na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the <hi>Turks</hi> had given Two hundred Baſtinadoes to an Embaſſadour of <hi>France,</hi> and 'twas his Opinion, Mr. <hi>De Vitry</hi> deſerv'd four hundred: The King of <hi>Poland,</hi> a ſagacious Prince, and great Politician, would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to ſay no more, for fear the heat he was in might tranſport him too far, hinder'd alſo the Entry of his Opinion upon their publick Records, contenting himſelf to let Mr. <hi>De Vitry</hi> know he had ſtrain'd his Character of Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour; Mr. <hi>De Vitry</hi> remain'd not long after this in <hi>Poland,</hi> and if ever he have Embaſſy elſewhere, I make no doubt the Princes they fend him to, will take due care to watch his Water. I have formerly toucht upon ſome circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> but as inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly I fell to other ſubjects, 'tis yet not unſeaſonable to relate what was the ſucceſs, though to have done
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:205236:43"/>things, exactly methodical it ſhould have been before handled. As the Conqueſt of <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> and the acquiſition of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal</hi> had ſtrangely alarm'd both Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and <hi>Spaniard,</hi> had been inſtant with all their Neigbouring Princes to uſe their Endeavours for their regaining of them again, but as ſome were feeble in all reſpects, others gain'd by the <hi>French,</hi> they remitted all to the Diet of <hi>Franckfort,</hi> where whole Months were ſpent in canvaſing a Paſs-port, four or five Months more took up in a debate whether they ſhould ſpeak <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> high <hi>Dutch</hi> or <hi>French,</hi> that ſo far from hopes of ſome Redreſs that way our Diſeaſe became the more incurable. Theſe delatories then making the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> deſpair of gaining their point by means of the Diet, they by concerted Meaſures march their Forces towards <hi>Strasburgh</hi> and <hi>Caſal,</hi> which the <hi>French</hi> was then beginning to fortifie, &amp; which lay almoſt every where open for that the old works had been thrown down to put new in the room:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:205236:43"/>The Emperor &amp; <hi>Spaniard</hi> were but in an ill condition to go through with any thing they undertook. But the King of <hi>France</hi> newly ſettled in his Conqueſt of thoſe two places, imagining they marcht not their Forces but with ſome deſign, and might not be without hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome private Intelligence in both the Towns, raiſes the <hi>Blocus</hi> of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> to have Forces in readineſs to oppoſe.</p>
            <p>Now as he was willing to have the thanks of that action, ſends for the Marquis of <hi>Fuentes</hi> Embaſſadour of <hi>Spain,</hi> to tell him, that upon the advice he had receiv'd the <hi>Turk</hi> was falling upon <hi>Hungary,</hi> he thought good to withdraw his Forces from <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> that ſo the King of <hi>Spain</hi> might have the greater liberty to aſſiſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror: The Marquis of <hi>Fuentes</hi> who knew well enough what to think of the Buſineſs, made his Compliment of thanks to his Majeſty notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as an act of great grace and favor, but amongſt Friends where he could be free, would be telling them what
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:205236:44"/>was the real cauſe of ſo great a change, which was in every Bodies mouth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready who had but the leaſt ſmacker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in publick Affairs: And indeed if I may be allow'd a little to argue the point, who is it does not ſee the art of this management was too too groſs to paſs upon good Eyes? For if true, <hi>France</hi> had ſuch good natur'd, and ſuch pious conſiderations, why has ſhe ſince contradicted them by ſo many of her actions to the contrary? why a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with <hi>Teckely?</hi> why Intregues carried on in <hi>Poland?</hi> why thoſe Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances with <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh?</hi> why Princes ſo warmly ply'd to draw them to her ſide? And in ſhort, why thoſe Huffs at the Imperial Diet, if they conſent not to her pretenſions? I know before hand what anſwer I ſhall have, I know nothing leſs will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd neither in regard to <hi>Teckely</hi> nor to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> that to what concerns the reſt will be anſwer'd, it was the Maſter-piece of a Politick King vers'd in King-craft, and the Arts of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:205236:44"/>Government to be making ſometimes ſuch ſort of Alliances which have their uſe, not ſo much in order to the ſupport of War abroad amongſt his Neighbours, as to hinder his Neighbours from car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the War home to his own door. I do know, as I ſaid, the unthinking part of Mankind may be put upon in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning of the one, and in giving ſome kind of gloſs to palliate the other, but I would a little fain know if they can anſwer this too which I am now about ſaying, <hi>France</hi> was willing to raiſe the <hi>Blocus</hi> of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> a whole year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Turks</hi> came down upon <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> and when effectually they came with a Vengeance he frames a Camp in <hi>Alſatia,</hi> to hold the Emperor in play, makes another in <hi>Flanders,</hi> to oblige <hi>Spain</hi> to be upon her Guard, a Camp upon the River <hi>Soare</hi> he orders, to frighten the Electors, and in fine, has another Camp drawn upon the <hi>Saonne</hi> to keep the reſt of <hi>Europe</hi> in a Jealouſie: <hi>France</hi> would ſhew to the World ſhe becomes leſs rapacious upon the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:205236:45"/>of the great misfortunes that hung now over the Head of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and when thoſe misfortunes are actually befallen her, it then Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Threats and Rants, and lets the Diet be roundly told he onely will give but ſuch certain ſhort day to grant her injuſt pretentions in and if not then granted would do her ſelf that right by force of Arms: And to be doing as well as ſaying, preſents with a great Army upon the Frontier, ready at a mouthfull to ſwallow ſeveral of the <hi>Spainiſh</hi> Provinces; War indeed they can't be ſaid to make, but make alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as much miſchief, by their hindring thoſe Princes which ſhe juſt dreaded as ſhe did the <hi>Turk,</hi> from em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying their Forces in favour of the Emperor: The Emperor indeed himſelf obliged to leave his to guard the <hi>Rhine,</hi> whilſt a Company of Infidels invades his Dominions, ravages to the very Heart of his Country, and carries off for Slaves a hundred Thouſand Souls, burns his Palaces, lays waſte the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:205236:45"/>round, and in concluſion claps Siege to <hi>Vienna,</hi> his Capital City, and place of Reſidence.</p>
            <p>But I perceive not all this while, that having but now documented others, I inſenſibly fall into the ſame Error my ſelf I would have them avoid: I fall off arguing the point, as if every one could not do it as well without me, let us have done then with theſe kind of entertainments, and go on to our Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of other places whether <hi>France</hi> aſpiring to the Univerſal Monarchy be Truth, or Fiction, or rather let us ſee if ſhe already uſurps not upon the right of Sovereigns as if ſhe actually were the Miſtreſs of the World: Let us ſee what ſhe is about, with her Mines in all the Courts of <hi>Europe;</hi> not that I pretend to ſay Policy is a thing forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den amongſt Princes, but that her meaning may no more be doubted of, every one can tell what an Errand ſhe ſent the Republic of <hi>Genoua,</hi> whoſe Coat ſhe fain would pick a hole in, ſends word ſhe will not have her put her
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:205236:46"/>Gally's out, leſt they ſhould come to joyn with thoſe of <hi>Spain,</hi> if otherwiſe ſhould take it for an act of Hoſtility, and ſhould uſe her accordingly as an Enemy declared: The <hi>Hollanders</hi> juſt ſo dealt with about a Month or two ſince, upon the intent they had of ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome new Ships to the King of <hi>Swede:</hi> So that over thoſe two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, where ſhe hath nothing to do, ſhe already Lords it as abſolute Sovereign, ſhe will not ſuffer Free States, who have bought their Liberty with the Price of their Blood ſhall think to make Alliances, and ſuccour their Allies, and they that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the eldeſt Sons of the Church can yet ſuffer an Alliance with her moſt mortal Enemy: But then let us ſee how ſhe deals with thoſe that leave her Intereſt, and thoſe it ſelf, who are mean ſpirited enough to adhere to her, let us look a little upon the different Springs ſhe ſets at work to bring her matters about; what ſays ſhe not of the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> for deſerting the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:205236:46"/>ſide, and his ſo very generouſly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing that of the Emperor; what does ſhe not at <hi>Leige,</hi> where ſhe makes it her Buſineſs to ſoment the Rebellion of that People againſt their lawful Prince, that ſo the Prince not able to maſter them, may not with the aſſiſtance of other Princes be in a poſt to make a Barrier of that City, and ſtop her paſſage that way into the Territories of other States? What does ſhe not act at <hi>Cullen,</hi> where the Inhabitants are all banding one againſt t'other, and cutting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Throats, whilſt the Enemy is at their Gates, ready to devour? What not at <hi>Hamburgh</hi> and <hi>Lubec,</hi> where Intregues apparent as the Sun are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on to the ruine both of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Country? What leave they undone in the Courts of the <hi>Lunebourg</hi> Princes, where People baniſht <hi>France</hi> are moſt in Credit, but baniſht after ſuch a faſhion as to return again into that Kingdom, when they will, and privately to ſee, and diſcourſe the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters? Indeed what is ſhe not brewing
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:205236:47"/>in the Emperors Court it ſelf, where ſhe foments Jealouſies among the chief, where ſhe opens the very Cabinet Counſels with her Silver Key, where not one reſolution can be taken, but ſhe gets notice of, at the ſame time? Some may ſay, I diſcourſe but of theſe affairs conjecturally: I ſhall moſt willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leave them to their own thoughts after, ſaying, what I have in anſwer.</p>
            <p>After the routing the Marſhal of <hi>Crequi</hi> at the Seige of <hi>Treves, France</hi> lay open to the prevailing ſide, there then ſtood no more Forces in their way, and had they been ſo minded might well have carried the Terror of their Arms into the Heart of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: The <hi>French</hi> were much afraid they would, and begun to pack their moſt valuable goods within the wall'd Towns, when Mr. <hi>De Louvois</hi> told a certain Perſon with whom I had par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular acquaintance during the time I was in <hi>France,</hi> and whom I have it from, that the Enemy would act no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Campagne, and were then
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:205236:47"/>upon their drawing off; I willingly would ask now if this was news one could reaſonably well credit in the then preſent poſture of Affairs, if one ought not to be ſupernaturally gifted, if one needed not a ſpirit of Revelation to be believing the contrary to what every one elſe had reaſon to believe: But what will not a Man do, as a certain old Author has remark't, who devotes his whole thought to become rich? To that very effect have the <hi>Suiſſes</hi> took the Bridle in their Mouths by the Fort of <hi>Huninghen,</hi> and made ſale both of Liberty and Country; a Counſellor of their State might remonſtrate his Heart out in full aſſembly, the Intereſt thoſe People had to be early in their oppoſition to a power, who in her am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious thoughts devour'd <hi>Europe,</hi> the Penſioners of <hi>France</hi> ſoon ſtops his Mouth, and as they ſtruck the greateſt ſtroke with that Common-wealth, muſt ſubmit to what they pleas'd to do: That way 'twas that Nation ſuffer'd without oppoſing the <hi>Franch</hi> County to be ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:205236:48"/>by <hi>France,</hi> from whence it might have hoped the ſpeedy aſſiſtance of a Neighbour: I ſpeak not of a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more things happen'd of the ſame batch in the time of the late Wars, will ſeem too ſuperannuated, and too tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling: For in fine, who is't, but right well knows that to be the opening Key the <hi>French</hi> have with unlockt the Gates of ſo many Towns; every one can tell 'tis with that Inſtrument ſhe renders all undertakings to her prejudice Abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and did retard the Seige of <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipsburgh;</hi> but 'twere too much work to ſay here how very uſeful their Coin has been in their regard, and how very prejudicial to the World beſides. And yet can't hold from ſpeaking of a late paſſage happen'd in <hi>Denmark,</hi> to ſhew ſhe is no ſuch ſquanderer neither of her Mony, as one would well ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, <hi>Denmark</hi> becoming Penſioner to <hi>France,</hi> or ſay rather took Her Money to act as <hi>France</hi> would have her, <hi>Mr. Colbert,</hi> through whoſe hands the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny went deſign'd for that Court, having
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:205236:48"/>fancy to try, how the <hi>Dane</hi> would take it to have his Penſion retrench't, caus'd write to that effect to the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour in <hi>Denmark</hi> by the Hand of <hi>Mr. Colbert De Croiſſy</hi> his Brother, whoſe Province 'tis to take care of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign</hi> Affairs; the Embaſſadour having receiv'd his Inſtructions went imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to wait upon the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> ſurprized in the higheſt Nature, at the proceeding told him, he had no anſwer to return, but ſhould give the King of <hi>France,</hi> one by the hands of his own Envoy then in Court, and at the ſame time ſend Directions to his Envoy to ſpeak to the King in the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and to let him know how ill he took it at his hands: The King told the Envoy of <hi>Denmark,</hi> that he underſtood not what 'twas he ſpoke to him about, that his Embaſſad our had acted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out order, that 'twas never his thought neither to add nor diminiſh any thing in the Treaty he had made with the King his Maſter, and ſhould call home his Embaſſadour to teach him under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:205236:49"/>thus things of his own Head, ſo the poor Embaſſadour was Sacrificed juſt like the Governor of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> diſown'd by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> as before related: <hi>France</hi> too diſowns her Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour to preſerve Amity with the Crown of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It now remains to inſpect the cauſe why <hi>France</hi> ſo potent in her Arms, and knowing how diſunited and divided were all her Neighbours, has for all that been ſo long without engaging. To this a reaſon is given with much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility, nor is there in it much of puzzle.</p>
            <p>The private Alliance ſhe had made with the <hi>Turks,</hi> was the String to her Bow ſhe moſt truſted to, but that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance could not be expected ſhould produce the wiſh't effect of a ſudden, for the Truce then a foot between the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror and the Port expired but in the Year 1682. and had a mind it ſhould expire firſt before any thing was to be undertaken, was not over ſure whether the <hi>Turks,</hi> whoſe Faith in that affair could not be well relied on, would ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:205236:49"/>declare againſt the Emperor, or whether would accept thoſe very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious Terms propos'd by the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts,</hi> ont'other hand ſhe was upon the fortifying of a world of places, where much time was requiſite to finiſh the works, and was againſt the Rules of common Policy, not to enter upon a War, till ſhe had ſeen thoſe places in ſome probable Perfection, and thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto truly one might do her that right ſhe had let ſlip no favourable occaſion, but on the contrary had been imprudently done to act otherwiſe: And indeed to ſhew clearly her Deſign was to draw her men into the Field from the very critical Minut: The <hi>Turks</hi> began the dance with theirs, that no ſooner had advice they had fall'n upon <hi>Hungary,</hi> but the King parts froms <hi>Verſailles</hi> to head their Army, at the ſame time a Detachment had already been drawn of thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp't upon the <hi>Saone,</hi> with orders for their March towards the Frontier, and nothing now in Mouths of the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:205236:50"/>
               <hi>French,</hi> but the beſeiging of <hi>Cullen</hi> or <hi>Philipsburgh,</hi> when all of a ſudden a very extraordinary piece of news alter'd the reſolutions of that Prince: he had heard the <hi>Hungarians</hi> had abandon'd the paſs at <hi>Raab,</hi> and that the <hi>Turks</hi> without the leaſt of ſtopping at <hi>Raab,</hi> or <hi>Comorra,</hi> as was pretended they would have ſtopt at, advance on with an innumerable, vaſt Army towards <hi>Vienna,</hi> which they had determin'd to beſeige: Now <hi>France</hi> was well enough ſatisfi'd the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhould make Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but ſorry they ſhould make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſter of the Empire which he now look't on as his proper Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: <hi>France</hi> truſted to their beſeiging <hi>Raab</hi> and <hi>Comorra</hi> places of great ſtrength both by Art and Nature, and that they would ſpend both their time and pains before they gain'd their point, in the <hi>interim</hi> made ſure of doing his own Buſineſs, and to oblige the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors ſeeing themſelves on all hands ſo ſurrounded with Enemies to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to what ſhe pleas'd her ſelf: Hoped
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:205236:50"/>after the reinforcing his own, with the Forces of the Empire, to march them ſtraight up to the <hi>Turk,</hi> &amp; force him to a Battel or to retire home again: Noble deſigns of a great Prince, and brim full of Ambition; But learning as I ſaid, the <hi>Turks</hi> had laid Seige to <hi>Vienna</hi> was oblig'd to take new meaſures: To that effect he found it was no more to his purpoſe to ſet upon the Empire which another was about taking the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of by the taking of a ſingle Town: For as that was the only place of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence it was poſſible for him indeed to have caus'd a great deal of deſolation, and terror of his ſide, but was the wrong way to ſettle in the Throne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> then choſe rather at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to take her proſpect of what might be the event of the Seige of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna,</hi> and ſend her Creatures about ſtill repreſenting to all the Princes of the Empire, how the Emperor was but a weak Prince, fitter to hold beads then a Scepter, and to fit in a Cloiſter by much then at Helm: That the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:205236:51"/>was Tottering, and even now ready to fall under his conduct, that henceforth they would need rather a ſtout, vigorous Prince, which with a Thouſand good qualities beſides un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood perfectly well that of Leading of an Army: That if the <hi>Turks</hi> come once to get <hi>Vienna,</hi> they ought all to expect no better then abſolute deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: That their true and only means to be ſecured from ſo imminent a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief was to implore the aid of the King of <hi>France,</hi> who would ſoon liſten to it, provided they elected the <hi>Dauphin</hi> King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> as 'twas a thing he had been inſtant with them for of a long time, they ſhould no ſooner have anſwer'd his deſire in that particular, the Face of their Empire ſhould ſoon ſee chang'd, that the Kings Forces lay ready at their Gates for their nearer aſſiſtance, and would in ſhort retrive the Empire again into that flouriſhing condition it had ever yet been in under its greateſt Emperors.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Furſtenburgh</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:205236:51"/>of <hi>Strasburgh</hi> de voted wholly to the Intereſts of <hi>France,</hi> who for ſome Years has been labouring to deliver up his Country, was one of thoſe moſt powerfully endeavor'd to inſinuate theſe kind of things: But the averſion the Empire had for the <hi>French</hi> in general, was ſo great, and ſo univerſal, ſo far from calling of them into their help, would have much ſooner call'd in the <hi>Turk:</hi> And indeed the <hi>Turk</hi> troubles no Body for his Religion ſake, leaving every one to his Liberty of Conſcience, keeping ſtrictly to their word, where they once give it, and provided their Tribute be but paid which you promiſe them, Exact no more, no Leeches there preying upon the Blood of the People to be ſeen as in <hi>France</hi> ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming under the Name of <hi>Partiſan,</hi> or Farmers of the Kings Revenue, there no laying of new Taxes upon every ſort of thing, or when neceſſity obliges them to lay any are taken off again, as the neceſſity ceaſes, the Souldier is not there ill handled, nor the Miniſters at
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:205236:52"/>every turn threatning to lay them by the heels; on the contrary the Sword-Man is in great eſteem amongſt them, and a brave Fellow there is not without his Mark of Diſtinction: In a word they had heard ſo much of the <hi>French</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and way of Government that they had reſolv'd as one Man to ſtand it out to the laſt then ever have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p>In vain then did all theſe good <hi>French</hi> men take the pains in giving out as I was ſaying they did: The King then ſeeing he loſt his time that way, reſolv'd upon the employing it ſomewhere elſe to better purpoſes, whilſt the occaſion was opportune; his Pretentions to the County of <hi>Aloſt</hi> he ſtill kept up, and ſo marches to <hi>Flanders</hi> ſide with his Forces, proceeds to nominating of his general Officers, which he is never accuſtom'd to do but upon the neck of a War, and in fine making all ready to enter upon the Country: But juſt upon the point of putting his deſign in execution, God
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:205236:52"/>was pleas'd to take out of this World the Queen his Wife, one of the beſt Princeſſes upon Earth, after a ſickneſs of two or three Days.</p>
            <p>Her Diſeaſe appear'd not viſibly dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and was but a ſwelling, which kindly enough inclin'd to ſuppuration, but the Doctors inſtead of letting Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have her Courſe which was e'en ready to throw off the malignity as I was ſaying, having through Ignorance let her Blood, contrary to the Opinion of Mr. <hi>Fagon</hi> her chief Phyſician, it ſtruck in again to the Heart, and kill'd her: So ſoon as the Queen's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition was perceiv'd Dangerous, the King had notice, who came preſently to her Chamber, and ſeem'd moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremly ſenſible, threw himſelf upon her Bed, with the Tears in his Eyes ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> but the Queens Eyes now ſetting in Head, and Death approaching died in his Arms without being able to anſwer: They had an Hour or two before given <hi>Emetick</hi> Wine but had not ſtrength enough
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:205236:53"/>to bear it, that inſtead of doing her good, ſerv'd only but to ſhorten her time, they forc't the King away from her, who lay taking on like wild in her Arms, and the Queen they left upon the Bed of State, till the next Day, then put her into a Coffin of Lead, placing inſtead of the Body a waxen Image made in reſemblance, which for Nine days together was ſerv'd up as if yet alive, or rather as if it was the Queen her ſelf: She was afterwards carried to St. <hi>Dennis</hi> the ordinary Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying place of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> with a Magnificence truly Royal: Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen thouſand Flambeauxs, Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred poor People clad in Black, beſides the Servants of her own Family, and thoſe of all the Princes, and Princeſſes of the Blood Royal, an infinite of other Perſons of the firſt quality, with an endleſs train of Coaches. Her Heart had been carried ſome days before to <hi>Val-de grace,</hi> and placed in the Nuns Quire, right againſt the Chappel, where is kept that of the Queen Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:205236:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Two or three days before the Queen dy'd, there happen'd a thing of an odd Nature enough: That Princeſs who was extremely addicted to her Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, having call'd for an <hi>Almanack</hi> to her Bed-ſide to ſee when ſuch a Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day would fall to which ſhe had a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Devotion, perceiv'd the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of the <hi>Almanack</hi> in his Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the Month <hi>July,</hi> foretold the withdrawing of a Prince, and Death of ſome great Lady who would be much regretted, and as the Prince of <hi>Condy</hi>'s leaving the Court, ſhew'd perfectly he had hit extreme right, She turns her ſelf to Madam <hi>La Marſhalle de Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miers</hi> Lady of her Bed-chamber, who ſtood at her Beds-head and askt if 'twas not ſhe they meant; The particular of this I had from Madam <hi>La Marſhalle d' Humiers</hi> her ſelf, and ſince have had the curioſity to view the <hi>Almanack,</hi> where thoſe very two things are litterally to be found. However the grief of the King ſlopt his <hi>Flanders</hi> expedition, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd immediately to St. <hi>Clou,</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:205236:54"/>the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi>'s Country Houſe, from thence to <hi>Fountain-bleau,</hi> where in vain they ſtrive to divert him, as the Queen took great pleaſure in that place made him often call to mind his Queen, tears are frequent in his Eyes, and nothing but length of time can make him forget her.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding they give out, he perſiſts ſtill in his great deſigns the Truth of which we ſhall ſoon Know with a little patience: But for me, I think God ſent him that affliction to move him, and that in a little time, he not only will leave <hi>Europe</hi> in Peace, but by joining his Arms with the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> will force the <hi>Turk</hi> to leave the Empire in quiet, which we ought all to wiſh.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <p>THis Book was given to the Bookſeller, the Fifteenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> by which 'tis to be ſeen, the Author muſt be well enough acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Buſineſs of <hi>Aloſt,</hi> the <hi>manifeſto</hi> in Relation to it being to come out upon the <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> and her Majeſty dying but the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205236:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
